<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Quickstart Guide</title>

  <section>
    <title>Getting Started with VE-Suite</title>

    <para>To install VE-Suite:</para>

    <para><orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the dependencies installer (vesuite_deps1.1.7.exe) and
          make a note of the folder</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Run the VE-Suite installer (vesuite1.1.7_11671.exe) and make a
          note of the folder location</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> You will need to
    know the folder locations later, so be sure to remember them or write them
    down.</para>

    <para>To start VE-Launcher:</para>

    <para><orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Double-click on the VE-Suite shortcut, which will be located
          on the desktop after VE-Suite is installed</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Point VE-Launcher to its dependencies. This directory should
          be named VE_Suite.#.#_Dependencies</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Once you have set the dependencies directory, click OK to open
          the VE-Suite Launcher window</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click the Launch VE-Suite ubtton to start VE-Suite</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist><emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> You can find more
    information about VE-Launcher's settings in Chapter 12 of the VE-Suite
    documentation.</para>

    <para>To view sample data in VE-Suite:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Click on the File menu, then click Open ...</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Navigate to the VE-Suite install location, then to the
        <code>share/vesuite/examples/simple</code> directory</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click on <code>simple.ves</code> to select it, then click Open
        to load it in VE-Suite. If the scene is not initially visible, hold
        down the right mouse button and drag up in the VE-Xplorer window to
        pull the camera back.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Loading Data and Connecting</title>

    <para>To create a new plugin:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use VE-Launcher to start VE-Suite, or click on the New Document
        button to clear the design space</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Double-click on the Available Plugins folder in the VE-Conductor
        Network window</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Double-click on the DefaultPlugin folder that appears below the
        Available Plugins folder</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Right-click on the gray DefaultPlugin box that appears in the
        pane on the right side of the Available Objects window to access the
        plugin's menu, and select the Geometry Config option</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A new window, the CADTree Manager, will open on the design
        canvas. To select a geometry file, right-click on the Model_Geometry
        icon in the canvas and select Add Node..., then Load CAD
        file...</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Another window will open. Choose the file type, then select the
        file and click Open</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Name the object you loaded, then click OK to insert it into the
        plugin</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click Close on the CADTree Manager</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To load the information for the plugin's node into the rest of
        VE-Suite, click on the Connection menu and then on Submit Job</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The starting logo in VE-Xplorer should be replaced by the objects in
    the plugins you submitted. If you cannot see the objects you loaded, hold
    down the right mouse button and drag up inside the VE-Xplorer window to
    pull back the camera. Continue doing so until you can see the
    scene.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
