<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="Code_Guidelines">
  <title>Code Guidelines</title>

  <section id="class_structure_guidelines">
    <title>Class Structure</title>

    <para>Only one public class is allowed per file. Every class name, macro,
    etc. starts with either "cfd" or "CFD" to avoid name clashes with other
    libraries. Classes should all start with "cfd" and macros or constants can
    start with either. Class names and file names are the same (e.g.,
    cfdContours class is declared in cfdContours.h and implemented in
    cfdContours.cpp). This makes it easier to find the correct file for a
    specific class. All instance variables are declared as protected. The user
    and application developer should access instance variables through Set/Get
    methods.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Always</emphasis> initialize member variables
    in the constructor.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="names_guidelines">
    <title>Names</title>

    <para>Make names clear. Try to spell out a name and not use abbreviations.
    This leads to longer names but it makes using the software easier because
    you know that the SetRasterFontRange method will always be called that,
    not SetRFRange or SetRFontRange or SetRFR. When the name includes a
    natural abbreviation such as OpenGL, keep the abbreviation and capitalize
    the abbreviated letters. Only use alphanumeric characters in names,
    [a-zA-z0-9]. Do not use underscores ("_"). For example, use
    exteriorSurface rather than exterior_Surface or _exteriorSurface. Use
    capitalization to indicate words within a name. For example, a class could
    be called cfdVectorTopologyFilter. Use "this" inside of methods even
    though C++ does not require you to. This really seems to make the code
    more readable because it disambiguates between instance variables and
    local or global variables. It also disambiguates between member functions
    and other functions.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="class_names_guidelines">
    <title>Class Names</title>

    <para>Class names are nouns and usually start with "cfd".</para>
  </section>

  <section id="variable_names_guidelines">
    <title>Variable Names</title>

    <para>Variable names are nouns and should begin with a lower case
    character.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="function_names_guidelines">
    <title>Function Names</title>

    <para>Function names are verbs (e.g., SetRasterFontRange) and start with
    an upper case letter.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="functions_and_arguments_guidelines">
    <title>Functions and Function Arguments</title>

    <para>Use "const" on any member function that does not change any data. It
    enforces the purpose of a function and allows for better compiler
    optimizations.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="variable_usage_guidelines">
    <title>C++ Style Variable Usage</title>

    <para>Declare variables where they are first used. C++ lifted this
    restriction from C for a reason. It makes code more modular and easier to
    understand, modify, and debug.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="braces_guidelines">
    <title>Braces</title>

    <para>Place brace under and inline with keywords:</para>

    <para><code> if ( condition ) while ( condition ) </code></para>

    <para><code> { { </code></para>

    <para><code> ... ... </code></para>

    <para><code> } }</code></para>

    <para>Use braces for all if, while, and do statements even if there is
    only a single statement within the braces.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="header_files_guidelines">
    <title>Header Files</title>

    <para>Header files are for declarations only. It is difficult to read and
    find code if source is in the declarations.</para>

    <para>The header file of the class should include only the superclass
    header file. If you need any other includes, include comment at each one
    describing why it should be included.</para>

    <para>Forward declare classes when possible in header files.</para>

    <para>Header files should use guards to prevent multiple inclusion. These
    guards should be defined in the style FILENAME_H, which is the filename
    written in all upper case with punctuation such as dots (".") replaced by
    underscores ("_").</para>

    <para><code> #ifdef CFDHEADER_H </code></para>

    <para><code> #define CFDHEADER_H </code></para>

    <para><code> ... </code></para>

    <para><code> #endif // CFDHEADER_H</code></para>

    <para>Comment the end of every <code>#endif</code>, as shown above. Nested
    <code>#ifdef</code> can be difficult to follow.</para>

    <para>A new line after the last <code>#endif</code> is required by some
    compilers.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="text_formatting_guidelines">
    <title>Text Formatting</title>

    <para>Limit lines to 80 characters.</para>

    <para>Three (3) space indentation – Set your editor to insert three spaces
    every time you hit the tab key.</para>

    <para>Insert whitespace for readability. This means that one blank line
    should occur between function definitions or between different blocks of
    code.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="namespaces_guidelines">
    <title>Namespaces</title>

    <para>Do not place the "using namespace" directive at global scope in a
    header file. This can cause lots of invisible conflicts that are hard to
    track. Keep "using" statements to implementation files (if at all).</para>

    <para>For standard namespace keywords (cout, cin, cerr, endl, vector,
    string), you must use "std::cout," etc.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="comments_guidelines">
    <title>Comments</title>

    <para>Comments must tell "why", not "what is happening." At every point
    where you had a choice of what to do, place a comment describing which
    choice you made and why.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="parens_guidelines">
    <title>Parens () with Key Words and Functions Policy</title>

    <para>Do not put parens next to keywords. Put a space between keywords and
    parens.</para>

    <para>Do not use parens in return statements when it is not
    necessary.</para>

    <para>Do put parens next to function names.</para>

    <para>Example:</para>

    <para><code> if ( condition ) while ( condition ) </code></para>

    <para><code> { { </code></para>

    <para><code> ... ... </code></para>

    <para><code> } } </code></para>

    <para><code> strcpy( s, s1 ); return 1;</code></para>
  </section>

  <section id="array_indexing_guidelines">
    <title>Array Indexing</title>

    <para>Single-character variable names can easily be mistaken for numbers
    ("i"s can sometimes look a lot like ones). Make the array index stand out
    with whitespace:</para>

    <para><code> array[ i ] = 0.0; </code></para>

    <para><code> array[ 1 ] = 0.0; </code></para>

    <para><code> array[ 2 ] = 0.0;</code></para>
  </section>

  <section id="Documentation">
    <title>Documentation</title>

    <para>The following sections provide guidelines for editing the VE-Suite
    documentation using Docbook.</para>

    <section id="GUI_Buttons">
      <title>GUI Buttons</title>

      <para>When referring to GUI buttons, use the Docbook "guibutton" tag,
      i.e., enter this:</para>

      <para><code> Click &lt;guibutton&gt;Launch VE-Suite&lt;/guibutton&gt; to
      close VE-Launcher and start VE-Suite.</code></para>

      <para>to yield this:</para>

      <para>Click <guibutton>Launch VE-Suite </guibutton>to close VE-Launcher
      and start VE-Suite.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Notes">
      <title>Notes</title>

      <para>When including an important note that you want to draw users'
      attention to, type "NOTE:" and tag it with Docbook "emphasis
      role='bold'" tag, i.e., enter this:</para>

      <para><code> &lt;emphasis
      role="bold"&gt;NOTE:&lt;/emphasis&gt;</code></para>

      <para>to yield this:</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE:</emphasis></para>
    </section>

    <section id="Referring_to_VE_Suite_Versions">
      <title>Referring to VE-Suite Versions</title>

      <para>When referring to a general version of VE-Suite or any application
      within VE-Suite, such as in a command, use "x.x.x" to refer to the
      version number rather than a number so the reference does not become
      outdated with future release versions. For example, in the following
      sentence, "vesuite.x.x.x.exe" and "vesuite_deps.x.x.x.exe" refer to
      whichever version of VE-Suite is being used, and the user would change
      "x.x.x" to the appropriate version number.</para>

      <para><code> One installer, vesuite.x.x.x.exe, contains the core
      VE-Suite binaries and .dll files, while vesuite_deps.x.x.x.exe contains
      the binaries and .dll files of the dependencies for the current release
      of VE-Suite.</code></para>

      <para>In some cases, you might need to refer to a specific version of
      VE-Suite, as in the following example:</para>

      <para><code> Starting VE-Suite was simplified with the release of
      version 1.0.0 via VE-Launcher. </code></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
