<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Design Review Tool</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>NOTE: This tool can only be used in a CAVE.</para>

    <para>The Design Review Tool is a collection of features that facilitate
    capturing design suggestions during the review process and enable users to
    interrogate the product under review.</para>

    <para>The Design Review Tool allows a user to:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Capture an image of the user's current view. This is essentially
        a virtual camera that is tied to the user's head position.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Toggle parts of the CAD model on and off.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Add a pointer to the scene to highlight a specific area of
        interest.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Virtual Camera</title>

    <para>The virtual camera allows you to take a picture of a scene. To turn
    on the virutal camera:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Turn on the Camera Manager</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Turn on Picture Mode</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Turn off the Camera Window</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To change the resolution of the image that is taken as well as the
    size of your view angle, select the appropriate resolution on the Aspect
    Ratio choice dialog on the Camera tab.</para>

    <para>Ensure that the Auto Computer Near/Far Plane is selected to ensure
    that you are capturing the image you intend to.</para>

    <para>Use Button 1 to take your picture. When you press Button 1, the view
    frustum is displayed. The picture is taken when you release Button
    1.</para>

    <para>Choose the the appropriate image directory to save the image.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the CAD Selection Tool</title>

    <para>The ability to turn components on and off is controlled through the
    Conductor preferences pane, The CAD Selection check box is located under
    the Xplorer Settings tab. You should no longer be required to check and
    uncheck this box whenever you launch VE-Suite. The preferences should now
    be sent on the fly when VE-Suite is launched.</para>

    <para>Button 0 toggles the selected CAD off.</para>

    <para>Button 4 toggles the previously selected CAD back on.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Virtual Pointer</title>

    <para>To use the Virtual Pointer, go to the Xplorer menu, choose Devices,
    and select Pointer. This will display an arrow that is tied to the
    configured device VESPointer.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
