<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Using Okino's Polytrans Software</title>

  <section>
    <title>Translating with Modeling in Pro/E</title>

    <section>
      <title>Assembly-level cuts</title>

      <para>Features added at the assembly level of the model tree that affect
      parts' appearance do not translate through PolyTrans. This includes
      cuts, holes, and welds made at the assembly. The following workarounds
      are available:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Open the affected parts individually and apply the operation
          necessary to transform the part at the part level</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Activate the parts and use references in the assembly to cut
          the parts individually. This method better follows the design intent
          of the assembly-level operations, but it can cause circular
          references if it is implemented improperly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Family tables</title>

      <para>Family tables can be used in Pro/E to define parts with repeated
      features and to define parts in different locations in the same
      assembly. This can simplify the creation of a large assembly, but
      problems can arise when the assembly is translated through
      PolyTrans.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Part appearance</title>

        <para>If the appearance if individual parts is dictated by a family
        table (e.g., a spring's length and compressions are determined by a
        family table), parts appear in the generic instance in the
        translation.</para>

        <para>A workaround for this problem is to save a copy to a different
        location and change the name of every part. This strips the family
        table information from the parts. A backup of the model does not strip
        the family tables and will not fix the translation problem.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Assembly location</title>

        <para>Items can be assembled in location using a family table. This
        can show two or more locations for an individual item (e.g., a stored
        location and a use location).</para>

        <para>A workaround for this is to open the instance that will be
        translated and make a backup of this assembly. If two different
        locations are desired in the translation, make two different backups,
        one of each location.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Coloration</title>

      <para>There are two separate issues with coloration:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Items that seem to be colored in Pro/E appear without color in
          the translation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Colors within Pro/E do not appear to match colors within
          PolyTrans or colors within VE-Suite</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section>
        <title>No colors within VE-Suite (blinding whiteness)</title>

        <para>This is usually a result of coloring at the assembly level. Most
        models that have this problem do not exhibit whiteness throughout the
        entire model; they only have a few parts with blinding
        whiteness.</para>

        <para>To fix this, clear all surfaces at the assembly level after
        saving any colors that you want from the model. Then create a map-key
        that colors, saves, and closes a part. After the map-key is created,
        you can color the model by opening each part and activating the
        map-key.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Colors in Pro/E</title>

        <para>Colors in Pro/E do not appear to match the colors within
        PolyTrans and VE-Suite because the lighting scheme in each program is
        different. The lighting scheme in Pro/E is relatively easy to change,
        but there is no known way to save the changes to apply automatically
        between sessions of Pro/E or to new windows that are opened. Changing
        the lighting within VE-Suite is much more difficult.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Missing parts</title>

      <para>If you have missing parts in your Pro/E assembly, the following
      steps should solve the problem.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>On the Hierarchy Optimizer, press the Option...</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Disable the "Delete hidden objects" checkbox</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>After import, select "Unhide all" from the Edit menu of the
          "Selector Window" menu. Those items will be on blanked layers
          according to Granite terminology.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Importing hoses and cables</title>

      <para>To import Pro/E hoses or cables, first save the data in the Pro/E
      neutral format. This format will preserve the hose and cable surfaces so
      they can be imported into PolyTrans and then into VE-Suite. During the
      import of the neutral format, choose a fine-grained tessellation so the
      hoses and cables have a realistic appearance.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Translating with Bentley Software</title>

    <para>The best way to import data from Bentley software is to use the u3d
    file format. This will preserve the hierarchy in the CAD assembly and
    preserve the BIM data potentially in the Bentley exported data.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Translating with AutoCAD Software</title>

    <para>The best file format for working with AutoCAD is the 3D AutoCAD
    format, or the DWF format. When importing data, uncheck the "import text"
    option under the Options dialog.</para>

    <para>If you do need text imported from the AutoCAD file, choose to export
    it as text in the osgPTExporter rather than as 3D data.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Translating with JT Files</title>

    <para>Always import PMI (Production Manufacturing Information) and use the
    highest level LOD for most cases. If you need to preserve the CAD
    hierarchy, do not optimize the hierarchy during import.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Translating with 3DS/Max Files</title>

    <para>Be sure to regenerate the normals for the model once it is imported.
    The lights, animations, and other non-polygonal data will not be exported
    to OSG, so there is no need to be concerned with importing it.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
