<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="Software_Development_Documents">
  <title>Software Development Documents</title>

  <para>The Department of Energy is funding a collaborative effort to develop
  new computer simulation tools that are capable of modeling advanced,
  next-generation power plants. As part of this effort, Reaction Engineering
  International, Iowa State University, and Carnegie Mellon University have
  begun development of a virtual engineering-based computational framework to
  facilitate these demanding modeling efforts.</para>

  <para>This new, open source framework provides significant features and
  capabilities including:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Distributed computing capabilities</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Platform independence</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Extensibility for component models</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Modern user interface</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Support for a hierarchy of component models (from detailed to
      simple)</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Comprehensive graphics capabilities including support for
      immersive facilities</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Component architecture software design</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The VE-Suite framework provides capabilities to fundamentally alter
  the traditional simulation process. Instead of engineers working with a
  number of disparate computational models, it is now possible to have a
  tightly integrated modeling environment where models interact in a seamless
  manner. A sophisticated user interface provides easy user interaction, and
  comprehensive two-dimensional and three-dimensional graphics capabilities
  exist for viewing plant configurations and simulation results.</para>

  <para>VE-Suite’s extensible software design allows users to easily
  incorporate component models and corresponding two-dimensional and
  three-dimensional graphical representations to create new, plug-and-play
  framework components. By design, the framework components can be distributed
  across computational resources (different computers connected to the
  internet or a local area network) to make the most efficient use of
  resources.</para>

  <para>Additional details about VE-Suite are available in:</para>

  <para>Swensen, D.A., Maguire, M., Yang, C., and Bockelie, M.J.,
  “Computational Frameworks for Practical, Engineering Applications,”
  presented at the SIAM Computational Sciences and Engineering Conference
  2005, Orlando, Florida, USA, February 12-15, 2005.</para>

  <para>Bockelie, M., Swensen, D.A., Denison, M.K., Maguire, M., Yang, C.,
  Chen, Z., Sadler, B., Senior, C.L., Sarofim, A.F. “A Computational Workbench
  Environment for Virtual Power Plant Simulation”, Contract DE-FC26-00NT41047,
  Final Report, December, 2004.</para>

  <para>Huang, G., Bryden, K. M., and McCorkle, D. S., “Interactive Design
  using CFD and Virtual Engineering,” In the Proceedings of the 10th
  AIAA/ISSMO Multidisciplinary Analysis and Optimization Conference,
  AIAA-2004-4364, September 2004.</para>

  <para>Bryden, K. M., Ashlock, D. A., Corns, S. M.. Graph based evolutionary
  algorithms. submitted to the IEEE Trans Evol Comput.</para>

  <para>Bryden, K. M., and McCorkle, D. S., “Virtual Engineering,” in
  preparation to submit to the Journal of Computing and Information Science in
  Engineering,.</para>

  <para>Bryden, K. M. and McCorkle, D. S., “VE-Suite: A Foundation for
  Building Virtual Engineering Models of High Performance, Low Emission Power
  Plants,” 29th International Technical Conference on Coal Utilization &amp;
  Fuel Systems, Clearwater, Florida, 38-46 (2004).</para>

  <para>McCorkle, D. S., Bryden, K. M., and Kirstukas, S. J.., “Building a
  Foundation for Power Plant Virtual Engineering,” 28th International
  Technical Conference on Coal Utilization &amp; Fuel Systems, Clearwater,
  Florida, 63-71 (2003).</para>

  <para>McCorkle, D. S., Bryden, K. M., and Ashlock, D. A., “Planned
  Tournament Selection,” Intelligent Engineering Systems Through Artificial
  Neural Networks - Proceedings of the Artificial Neural Networks in
  Engineering Conference, 13: pp 385-390 (2003).</para>

  <para>McCorkle, D. S., Bryden, K. M., and Swensen, D. A., “Using Virtual
  Engineering Tools to Reduce NOx Emissions,” in the Proceedings of ASME Power
  2004, POWER2004-52021, pp 441-446, March 2004.</para>
</chapter>
