<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Creating Content in VE-Suite</title>

  <section>
    <title>Loading Data and Connecting</title>

    <para>VE-Suite loads objects through plugins. This section describes how
    to load a geometry file through a plugin. Other data files may be loaded
    in the same manner.</para>

    <para>Plugins are set up through the Available Objects window. Click on
    the New Document button to make sure the design space is clear.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Clearing the design space</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-cleardesignspace.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To create a new plugin, double-click on the DefaultPlugin directory
    below the Available Plugins directory in the VE-Conductor Network
    window.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>VE-Conductor Network window</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins03.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Right-click on the gray DefaultPlugin box that appears in the pane
    on the right side of the window to access the plugin's menu, and select
    the Geometry Config option.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Select the Geometry Config option</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins04.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>A new window, the CADTree Manager, will open. This holds the objects
    that are inserted into the plugin. To select a geometry file, right-click
    on the Model_Geometry icon and select Add Node..., then Load CAD
    file...</para>

    <figure>
      <title>To select a geometry file, click Load CAD file...</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins06.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In the dialog box that opens, choose the appropriate file type, then
    select the file and click the Open button.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Loading a CAD file</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins07.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Name the object you loaded, then click the OK button to insert it
    into the plugin.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Name the CAD object</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins08.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Click Close on the CADTree Manager.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Close the CADTree Manager before loading the plugin
      information</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins09.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To load the information for the plugin's node into the rest of
    VE-Suite, click on the Connection menu and select Submit Job.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Click Submit Job to load the information into the rest of
      VE-Suite</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins10.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The starting logo in Xplorer should be replaced by the objects in
    the plugins you submitted.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Use the keyboard or mouse to manipulate the camera and bring the
      object into view</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins11-cropped.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If the object is not initially visible in the Xplorer window, it may
    be outside the viewing region. Hold down the right mouse button and drag
    up in the Xplorer window to pull back the camera. Continue doing so until
    the scene is visible in the Xplorer window.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Geometry In Depth</title>

    <para>In addition to allowing users to load multiple geometry objects,
    VE-Suite also allows objects to be transformed, shaded, and
    textured.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Loading Objects and Assemblies</title>

      <para>To load multiple geometry objects in VE-Suite, continue adding CAD
      file nodes in the same way that you loaded a single CAD file.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>To load multiple geometry objects, continue adding CAD file
        nodes</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-plugins06.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If you want to load multiple instances of the same object, its CAD
      file can be loaded multiple times. However, that wastes memory. A better
      way to load multiple instances of the same object is to load the object
      into the scene one time, then clone the other instances from it to save
      memory. To clone an object, right-click on it and select Clone
      Node…</para>

      <figure>
        <title>To load multiple instances of the sae object, select Clone
        Node...</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-clone-node.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>New assemblies can also be created for grouping geometry objects.
      Right-click the appropriate assembly, then select Add Node..., then
      Create New Assembly...</para>

      <figure>
        <title>New assemblies can be created for grouping geometry
        objects</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-create-new-assembly.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To quickly populate an assembly, the entire geometry object tree
      can be loaded from another project. First, select the appropriate
      geometry tree in the CADTree Manger, then click the Save As... button to
      save it as a <code>.veg</code> file.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Loading a geometry object tree</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-save-as-veg.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Next, open the geometry tree where the first geometry tree is to
      be moved, right-click the assembly where it is to be moved, then select
      Add Node, then Load VEG file.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Transforming Geometric Objects</title>

      <para>Geometric objects can be moved, rotated, and scaled in the scene
      by using the Transformation dialog. To open the Transformation dialog,
      open the CADTree Manager, right-click on the object to be transformed,
      and select Properties. This will open the CAD Properties window. The
      Transformation dialog is the first tab in the CAD Properties
      window.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>CAD Properties window</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-transform-dialog.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When you edit the Transform properties, the scene is updated in
      real time. Once the object's size and placement are satisfactory, click
      OK.</para>

      <para>An assembly's transform properties can also be edited, but keep in
      mind that an assembly’s transformation also affects its members. See the
      Chapter 3.2, Geometry In-Depth, for more information on
      assemblies.</para>

      <!-- TODO: add olink for Chapter 3 -->
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Toggling Geometric Objects</title>

      <para>You can toggle the visibility of geometric objects on and off. To
      do so, right-click the object in the CADTree Manager and select Toggle
      Node, then On or Off.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Materials and Shaders</title>

      <para>You can apply custom materials and shaders to geometric objects.
      Right-click the object and select Properties. When the CAD Properties
      window opens, select the Attributes tab. Choose Materials or Shaders,
      then click Add....</para>

      <para>If you choose Materials, you will be asked to name the material.
      Once it is in the list, you can apply it to the object by left-clicking
      it. To change a material's properties, right-click its name. A menu will
      appear with options to change its lighting, shininess, opacity, and how
      the lighting and material are applied to the object.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Applying materials and shaders to geometric objects</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-cadproperties-attributes.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If you choose Shaders, you will be asked to load a shader .
      Example shaders can be found in the
      <code>VE-Suite_x.x.x\share\vesuite\shaders</code> directory. You can
      apply a shader by clicking on its name, the clicking the Open
      button.</para>

      <para>A material and a shader cannot both be added to an object at the
      same time. To remove a material or shader from an object, click Restore
      Defaults. To remove a material or shader from the Available Attributes
      list, select its name and click the Remove... button.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Coloring Geometric Objects</title>

      <para>The geometry's color is determined by its Material attribute. To
      change the Material attribute, open the geometry's Properties, go to the
      Attributes tab, and right-click the Material attribute to be
      changed.</para>

      <para>On Windows, the color dialog box looks like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Windows color dialog box</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-windows-palette.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>A color can be chosen from the Basic colors palette, or the color
      map and luminosity slider can help you create custom colors. Custom
      colors do not need to be added to the Custom colors palette. They will
      be forgotten once the dialog is closed.</para>

      <para>When creating a custom color, make sure to check the luminosity
      slider as well as the Color/Solid preview box next to the Hue/Sat/Lum
      values. The color will appear as black or white if the luminosity slider
      is set too high or too low.</para>

      <para>Click OK to set the new color.</para>

      <para>On non-Windows systems, the color dialog box looks like
      this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Non-Windows color dialog box</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-non-windows-colorwheel.jpg"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>A color can be chosen from the Palette, or the color ring and
      triangle can be used to create a custom color. The bar below the color
      ring shows the current color on the left and the new color on the
      right.</para>

      <para>To make a custom color, choose its hue by clicking in the color
      ring, then choose its saturation and value by clicking in the color
      triangle. Click OK to set the new color.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Assemblies</title>

      <para>Assemblies group geometric objects together so they can all be
      modified at once. An assembly's properties are passed to its members and
      can change its members in the following ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Transformation: Member translations are relative to their
          assembly's axes, not the world's axes. Member scalings are relative
          to their assembly's scalings (e.g., if you double the scale of a
          member whose assembly is already double-scaled, the member will be
          scaled to four times the original size). Assemblies rotate around
          the assembly's origin point, not members' origin points.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Materials and Shaders: Materials and shaders applied to
          assemblies are applied to its members. If a member is assigned a
          material or shader as well, the member's material or shader
          overrides its assembly's material or shader.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Toggle node: Toggling an assembly Off hides all of its
          members. Toggling an assembly On shows any members that are toggled
          On. If a member is toggled Off, togging its assembly On will not
          reveal that member.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Navigation</title>

    <para>There are two ways to manipulate VE-Suite's view using just the
    mouse: dragging in the Xplorer window itself or using the Navigation Pane.
    A RemotePoint RF wand can also be used to navigate VE-Suite.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Xplorer Window</title>

      <para>A three-button mouse will enable a user to do every translation
      and rotation within the Xplorer window itself.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Rotating a scene</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-3button-nav.gif"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To rotate the scene, drag along the screen while holding the left
      button. To rotate along the X- and Z-axes, drag in the center of the
      screen. To rotate along the Y-axis, drag along the border of the
      screen.</para>

      <para>The right mouse button handles Y-axis translations. Hold the right
      button and drag the mouse up or down to push the scene away or pull it
      closer.</para>

      <para>The mouse wheel button handles the other translations. Hold it
      down to drag the scene left, right, up, or down across the
      screen.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE:</emphasis> Returning to the original
      orientation after rotating the scene may be difficult. This is because
      the mouse controls rotate around an arbitrary axis that allows rotation
      in all three dimensions, but it can be difficult to return to a previous
      orientation. To return to a standard orientation, select the View
      submenu under the VE-Xplorer menu, then click on either Reset or Frame
      All.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Navigation Pane</title>

      <para>To open the Navigation Pane, select it from the VE-Xplorer
      menu.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Select Navigation Pane from the VE-Xplorer menu</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-navpane-01.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The Navigation Pane looks like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Navigation Pane</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-navpane-02.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Experiment with the movement buttons (the ones with arrows on
      them) to see how they change the scene. Note that they move the camera,
      not the object. Clicking the X-axis button, for example, will move the
      camera left, making the object shift right.</para>

      <para>Most of the other controls modify how the movement buttons
      act:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Step Size sliders control the speed of translations and
          rotations. The farther to the right they are, the faster
          translations and rotations occur.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Rotate About Users Head checkbox controls how the camera
          reacts to Yaw Rotation commands. If it is checked, the camera
          rotates in place. If it is not, the camera rotates around the
          environment center, like roll and pitch rotations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Rest Nav Position button resets the camera to its initial
          position.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Lower Limit checkbox sets whether movement in the
          z-direction can be negative.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The Store Start Position button allows an initial position to
          be stored for the model.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Wands</title>

      <para>With the proper Juggler configuration, wands can be used to
      navigate VE-Suite. Once the wand is set up, pressing the Nav button and
      holding the wand moves you in that direction. Holding down the Left
      Shoulder button and pointing to the left will rotate the camera to its
      left.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Wands can be used to navigate VE-Suite</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/03-remotediagram.jpg"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Keyboard/Mouse Navigation Scheme</title>

      <para>A keyboard/mouse navigation scheme can also be used to navigate in
      VE-Suite.</para>

      <table>
        <title>Axes</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>x-axis</entry>

              <entry>left to right</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>y-axis</entry>

              <entry>near to far</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>z-axis</entry>

              <entry>bottom to top</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <table>
        <title>Modifier Keys</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>None</entry>

              <entry>Yes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Shift</entry>

              <entry>Yes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Ctrl</entry>

              <entry>No</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Alt</entry>

              <entry>No</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Trackball Mode:</emphasis></para>

      <table>
        <title>Keyboard Commands</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>R</entry>

              <entry>Reset the center point and camera transform</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>F</entry>

              <entry>Frame all geometry within the current viewing
              frustum</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>A</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>S</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>W</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>D</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>C</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Space Bar</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>K</entry>

              <entry>SkyCam() function</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Up Arrow</entry>

              <entry>Positive zoom in the yz-axes 45 degrees</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Down Arrow</entry>

              <entry>Negative zoom in the yz-axes 45 degrees</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Left Arrow</entry>

              <entry>Negative pan in the x-axis</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Right Arrow</entry>

              <entry>Positive pan in the x-axis</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <table>
        <title>Mouse Commands</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Left mouse button - mod:none</entry>

              <entry>Rotate about the xz-axes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Left mouse button - mod:none; on edges of window</entry>

              <entry>Twist about the y-axis</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Middle mouse button - Scroll Up</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Middle mouse button</entry>

              <entry>Pan in the xz-axes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Middle mouse button - Scroll Down</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Right mouse button</entry>

              <entry>Zoom in/out along the y-axis</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Character Mode (1st- and 3rd-person
      views):</emphasis></para>

      <table>
        <title>Keyboard Commands</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>A</entry>

              <entry>Strafe left</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>S</entry>

              <entry>Walk/Run backward</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>W</entry>

              <entry>Walk/Run forward</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>D</entry>

              <entry>Strafe right</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>C</entry>

              <entry>Fly down (not implemented)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Space Bar</entry>

              <entry>Jump/Fly up (not implemented)</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <table>
        <title>Mouse Commands</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Left mouse button</entry>

              <entry>Rotate the camera about the xz-axes</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Left mouse button - mod:shift</entry>

              <entry>Physics picking using Bullet p2p constraint</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Middle mouse button - Scroll Up</entry>

              <entry>Zoom in to the character</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Middle mouse button</entry>

              <entry><emphasis>not currently used</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Middle mouse button - Scroll Down</entry>

              <entry>Zoom out from the character</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Right mouse button</entry>

              <entry>Rotate the camera and the character about the
              xz-axes</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Viewpoints Pane</title>

    <para>To store multiple viewpoints and switch between them, use the
    Viewpoints Pane under the VE-Xplorer menu.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Viewpoints Pane</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-viewpoints-pane.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When the Viewpoints Pane starts, no viewpoints are loaded. As the
    user adds them to the pane, they appear in the Move to a Viewpoint
    dropdown menu, which can be used to select the viewpoint the user wants to
    switch to.</para>

    <para>To add a viewpoint, position the camera the way you want it in the
    viewpoint, then click the Add Location button. The viewpoint will be added
    to the dropdown menu.</para>

    <para>Viewpoints can be deleted by clicking the Delete Location(s) button,
    selecting the appropriate viewpoint from the window that opens, and
    clicking OK.</para>

    <para>Once a viewpoint is added, the
    <code>stored_viewpts_flythroughs.vel</code> file in the working directory
    is updated. It is automatically updated when a viewpoint is added or
    deleted. Saved viewpoints can be restored later by clicking the Load
    button.</para>

    <para>To move to a viewpoint, select it from the dropdown menu in the
    Flythrough Control section of the Viewpoints Pane. The camera will fly to
    that viewpoint at the speed set in the speed scroller.</para>

    <para>Viewpoints can also be cycled through a flythrough. Click on the
    Start button below Automate Flythrough to begin a flythrough between each
    viewpoint in successive order. The flythrough will start at the first
    viewpoint, then hit each successive viewpoint, going at the speed
    specified by the speed scroller. When it reaches the last viewpoint, it
    will go back to the first one and repeat the flythrough. To stop the
    flythrough at any time, click the Stop button.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Xplorer Displays</title>

    <para>A frames-per-second (FPS) counter and a coordinate compass can be
    displayed in the VE-Xplorer window.</para>

    <para>To display the FPS counter, go to the VE-Xplorer menu and select
    Display, then Frame Rate. VE-Xplorer will display the FPS in the lower
    right corner of its window.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Displaying the frame rate</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/03-frame-rate.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To display the coordinate compass, go to the VE-Xplorer menu and
    select Display, then Coord System. VE-Xplorer will display the coordinate
    compass in the upper left corner of its window.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Quitting VE-Suite</title>

    <para>Ending a VE-Suite session requires two steps:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select Quit from VE-Conductor's File menu. This quits
        VE-Conductor and VE-Xplorer.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select the shell window running the Name Server. Click the
        Shutdown Name Server button or press Ctrl+C to close the
        program.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
