<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Vehicle Design Review Tools</title>

  <para>NOTE: These tools can only be used in a CAVE.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Dynamic Vehicle Simulator Tool</title>

    <para>The Dynamic Vehicle Simulator Tool is a plugin to VE-Xplorer and
    VE-Conductor that enables mapping global positioning data to user-selected
    CAD.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring the Simulator</title>

      <para>Coming soon</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring the Graphics</title>

      <para>Coming Soon</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Registration Tools</title>

    <para>The Registration Tools enable users to position a vehicle buck in a
    tracked environment for the purpose of registering a digital CAD
    representation of the vehicle buck to the physical buck.</para>

    <para>Information users should know before using the Registration
    Tools:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The CAD should be pointed forward in the environment. NOTE: This
        is only applicable if the user is not going to also use the Dynamic
        Vehicle Simulator Tool.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The CAD needs to be scaled to feet.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The tracking markers only need to be present on the buck during
        the registration process. Once the buck is registered, the markers can
        be removed and used for other purposes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The Seat Index Position (SIP) measurement is the distance from
        the origin of the CAD model to the SIP in the model. The coordinate
        system for this measurement is Y toward the front of the vehicle, X to
        the right of the vehicle, and Z to the top of the vehicle. This is
        typically measured in a CAD package or in a review tool like
        TeamCenter.</para>

        <para>Example code for the tracking marker configuration file:</para>

        <para><code># The measurements are in mm </code></para>

        <para><code># The coords are x to the rear, y up, z to the left
        </code></para>

        <para><code># The order is Front, Left Rear, Right Rear </code></para>

        <para><code>VJHead -1048.1 686.8 13.3 </code></para>

        <para><code>VJWand 597.8 792.5 421.4 </code></para>

        <para><code>VESPointer 600.9 792.4 -421.4 </code></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Using the Registration Tools</title>

      <para>Follow these steps to use the Registration Tools:</para>

      <para><orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Place the tracking markers in the appropriate locations on
            the vehicle buck.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Update the tracking marker configuration file with the
            measured data for the location of the tracking markers to the
            SIP.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Update the tracking marker configuration file with the bird
            locations on the buck as follows:</para>

            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The first listed marker is the front of the buck</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The second listed marker is the left rear of the
                buck</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The third listed marker is the right rear of the
                buck</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Load the CAD and position and scale it appropriately based
            on the assumptions listed above.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Choose the file button and select the tracking marker
            configuration file.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Press the registration button.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>At this point, the CAD should be aligned with the
      vehicle buck.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
