<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Dependencies</title>

  <para>The following is a list of links for the VE-Suite dependencies.
  Dependencies can be downloaded and built by the user from the following
  links or the pre-compiled binaries can be installed from the download
  page.</para>

  <para><link
  xlink:href="http://www.openscenegraph.org/projects/osg">OpenSceneGraph
  (OSG)</link> is used to manage the scenegraph (verson 1.2+)</para>

  <para><link
  xlink:href="http://www.vtk.org/VTK/resources/software.html#interim">VTK</link>
  is used to render the visualization objects (version 5.0+)</para>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://www.cmake.org/HTML/Index.html">CMake</link>
  is needed to build the VTK</para>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/vrjuggler/files/">VR
  Juggler</link> is used for management of the virtual environment (version
  2.0.1+)</para>

  <para>The dependencies are best installed in the following order:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>CMake</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>VR Juggler</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>OpenSceneGraph</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>VTK</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/vrjuggler/files/">VR
  Juggler dependencies zip file</link></para>

  <para>VR Juggler has its own set of dependencies if you are building it
  yourself:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>GMTL 0.4.12+</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Boost 1.33 1+</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Cppdom 0.6.6+</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>openAL 0.0.8+</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>omniORB 4.1.0+</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>VRPN 0.7.03+</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/download.html">Java 2
  SDK</link> is needed for Juggler's java-based VRJconfig program.</para>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://www.wxwidgets.org/">wxWidgets</link> is used
  to compile and run the GUI. (Click "download" on the left side menu to get
  to the files.) (version 2.6.2+)</para>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://xerces.apache.org/">Xerces</link> is used to
  read and write XML. (Download <link
  xlink:href="http://xerces.apache.org/xerces-c/download.cgi">xerces-c-current</link>)
  (version 2.7.0+)</para>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://download.dre.vanderbilt.edu/">ACE/TAO</link>
  is used for cross-platform communications. (ACE version 5.5+, TAO version
  1.5+)</para>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://apr.apache.org/">APR</link> is used to
  generate the GUIDs. (version 1.2.8)</para>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://opal.sourceforge.net/">OPAL</link> (Open
  Physics Abstraction Layer) is used as a wrapper to ODE for physics
  integration. (version 0.4.0)</para>

  <para><link xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/opende/">ODE</link>
  (Open Dynamics Engine) is used for physics integration. (version 0.7)</para>

  <para>VE-Launcher was coded using <link
  xlink:href="http://www.python.org/">Python</link>. It can run in Python2.3
  or higher. If you are running it from Python, you need to install these
  extensions for Python as well:</para>

  <para>Windows: VE-Launcher requires these <link
  xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/pywin32/files/">Win32</link>
  extensions if you are running it in Python for Windows.</para>

  <para>VE-Launcher requires <link xlink:href="http://wxpython.org/">wxPython
  2.6.3.3 </link>if you are running it in Python.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Development Dependency Guidelines</title>

    <para>To avoid dependencies problems during development, we have provided
    guidelines for using dependencies with VE-Suite. These are the guidelines
    the main VE-Suite development group follows and are provided as
    suggestions for other users.</para>

    <para>Windows:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The developer must either download all the installers for a
        particular windows IDE and OS, or build all the dependencies for
        VE-Suite themselves.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The VE-Suite development team will maintain certain installers
        for all dependencies so that the external developers will have easier
        access to the current development tools.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The development libraries will be kept in the native directory
        structure for a respective library. This ensures that a developer is
        able to swap libraries as necessary for research purposes without
        having to change the build system.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Linux:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The developer must either download all of the dependencies'
        rpms, use their platform's respective package management system, or
        build all of the dependencies for VE-Suite themselves.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The VE-Suite development team will maintain rpm files for all
        dependencies so that the external developers will have easier access
        to the current development tools.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>On Linux platforms, the dependency directory structure will be
        assumed to be include, bin, lib, and share as is the case for most
        libraries when the install target is used on a build system.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Building Dependencies on Windows</title>

    <para>It is best to read the specific installation/build instructions for
    each dependency before attempting to build. The information provided
    includes specific details to allow VE-Suite to build/run correctly.</para>

    <para>VE-Suite and its dependencies are currently built and tested using
    Visual Studio 8.0(2005).</para>

    <para>You can find the development libraries at <link
    xlink:href="http://www.vesuite.org/external/deps/non-admin/">http://www.vesuite.org/external/deps/non-admin/</link>.</para>

    <para>Notes on installing dependencies:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link
        xlink:href="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/">TortoiseSVN</link> - Used
        to check out and update VE-Suite from ISU's code repository.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>After TortoiseSVN is installed, you can check out the code if
        you have an account registered with ISU's repository. Create a
        VE-Suite directory. Right-click on the VE-Suite directory and choose
        "Checkout..."</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Alternately, if you get the VE-Suite source code as a compressed
        tarball, some unzip utilities may not maintain the correct directory
        structure. This can be fixed by unzipping the files on a Unix-based
        system and then moving the files to the Windows machine.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>While the default locations for installations will work, we
        recommend creating a directory in the root (<code>C:</code>) directory
        to minimize the path lengths and the accompanying potential for typos
        when configuring environment settings.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>VE-Suite Component Dependencies</title>

    <para>If you are installing individual components of VE-Suite on different
    desktops, it is only necessary to install the dependencies for that
    specific component. Below is a table listing the individual components and
    their specific dependencies.</para>

    <table>
      <title>Component Dependencies</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Computational Engine</entry>

            <entry>ACE/TAO, xerces-c</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>VE-Conductor (GUI)</entry>

            <entry>ACE/TAO, xerces-c, wxWidgets</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>VE-Xplorer</entry>

            <entry>ACE/TAO, OpenSceneGraph, VTK, VR Juggler</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Other Requirements</title>

    <para>Computers running VE-Suite must be able to run all of the
    dependencies listed above. They must also have shader support. VE-Suite
    will not run properly without shader support.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
