<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Installation and Setup</title>

  <para>Support is provided at the following locations:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><link
      xlink:href="https://subversion.vrac.iastate.edu/Subversion/TSVEG/Bugzilla/">VE-Suite
      Bugzilla</link>, VE-Suite's interface for bug tracking. Users and
      developers can view and submit bugs.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>An email list for VE-Suite users will be set up soon</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Installation of VE-Suite is fairly straightforward. Visit the <link
  xlink:href="http://www.vesuite.org/download.php">Downloads</link> section
  and locate your operating system.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows:</emphasis> Two installers are provided
  for Windows. Each installer will guide you through the process of selecting
  various options. One installer, <code>vesuite#.#.#_####.exe</code>, contains
  the core VE-Suite binaries and <code>.dll</code> files. The dependencies
  installer, <code>vesuite_deps#.#.#.exe</code>, contains the binaries and
  <code>.dll</code> files of VE-Suite's dependencies, arranged to include
  <code>bin</code>, <code>lib</code>, and <code>share</code>
  subdirectories.</para>

  <para><emphasis role="bold">Unix:</emphasis> A <code>tar.gz</code> file of
  the current release of VE-Suite is provided. You can extract the
  <code>VE-Suite.#.#.#</code> directory from it. Instead of one central
  dependencies directory, we provide the dependencies' rpm files. Be sure to
  install the necessary dependencies before running VE-Suite.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Windows Installation</title>

    <para>Installing VE-Suite and its dependencies follows the same procedures
    as other installations. The user chooses which components to install,
    their locations, their Start Menu folder, and whether to add an icon to
    the desktop.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Installing VE-Suite</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata contentdepth="" contentwidth="" depth=""
                     fileref="images/windowsinstallsetup.png" scalefit="1"
                     width=""></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>One important consideration is which components to install. In large
    setups, certain computers will run the NameServer while others will handle
    VE-Conductor and VE-Xplorer. To run VE-Suite on a single desktop, leave
    all of the checkboxes checked to install everything.</para>

    <para>Go through the same process for VE-Suite's dependencies.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Unix Installation</title>

    <para>On Unix, the installers are compressed <code>tar.gz</code> files.
    Open them using these commands:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Using GNU tar: <code>gtar xvzf
        vesuite_#.#.#_RHEL_4.tar.gz</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Using gzip: <code>gunzip &lt; vesuite_#.#.#_RHEL_4.tar.gz | tar
        xvf –</code></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE: </emphasis>These examples use
    <code>vesuite_#.#.#</code> as a general placeholder for any version of
    VE-Suite. Be sure to change the version number to the specific version you
    are installing.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting the Runtime Environment</title>

    <para>In previous versions, VE-Suite's runtime environment was set through
    text scripts. Now it uses VE-Launcher to set up the environment. Most of
    it is automated, but you should be aware of two important variables it
    sets: VE-Suite's directory and VE-Suite's dependencies directory.</para>

    <para>VE-Launcher automatically determines VE-Suite's directory from the
    current working directory. <emphasis role="bold">Moving VE-Launcher out of
    VE-Suite's directory or starting it from a different directory will pass
    the wrong value to VE-Suite, causing errors.</emphasis></para>

    <para>The dependencies directory is the only variable that needs to be set
    manually. The first time you start VE-Launcher, you will be asked to find
    the dependencies directory. On Windows, the dependencies directory is
    <code>VE_Suite.#.#.#_Dependencies</code>.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Setting dependencies on Windows</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/01-browse.jpg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>On UNIX/Linux, multiple dependencies can be chosen. The only one
    that needs to be specifically selected is VR Juggler's directory.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Setting dependencies on UNIX/Linux</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/01-linux-set-deps.jpg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If you are upgrading from an earlier version of VE-Suite, the
    dependencies' directories can be changed by selecting the dependency and
    clicking the Delete button, or clicking the Add button and selecting a new
    directory.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting Menus, Icons, and Filetypes on Linux</title>

    <para>VE-Suite comes with a <code>vesuiteConfig.sh</code> script to set up
    menus, icons, and filetypes for VE-Suite on Linux desktop systems. The
    script works for Gnome 2.8+ and KDE.</para>

    <para>To run it, go to its directory and enter
    <code>./vesuiteConfig.sh</code>, followed by the arguments. The script
    accepts these arguments:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>--gnome</code> or <code>--kde</code>: Sets Gnome or KDE as
        a primary desktop. If you do not provide either argument, Gnome will
        be chosen as the default primary desktop.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>--both</code>: Installs on both Gnome and KDE.
        <code>--gnome</code> or <code>--kde</code> still needs to be provided
        to set the primary desktop, because on most dual-desktop systems, one
        desktop inherits some preferences from the other.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>--user</code> or <code>--global</code>: Sets the
        installations to either user-only or all-users. If you do not provide
        either argument, all-users will be chosen if you have root access.
        Otherwise, only the current user (user-only) is chosen.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>--uninstall</code>: Uninstalls the setup defined by the
        other arguments on the command line. For example, <code>--gnome
        --global --uninstall</code> would uninstall the setup created by
        providing <code>--gnome --global</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
