<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Launcher</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>VE-Launcher is a quick and easy way to launch any configuration of
    VE-Suite. It helps users save configurations, choose which programs to
    run, and launch them without entering text commands. Because so many
    options and configurations are available, choosing the necessary one can
    take some work. This chapter explains how to use VE-Launcher and includes
    an example setup.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting VE-Launcher</title>

    <para>VE-Launcher is started differently on Windows and Unix installs. On
    Windows, double-click the VE-Launcher executable. On a Unix-based install,
    VE-Launcher is a Python program. Go to VE-Suite’s <code>/bin</code>
    directory and run <code>velauncher.py</code>. Specifically, from the
    command line, enter the <code>/bin</code> directory and type <code>python
    velauncher.py </code>to run VE-Launcher.</para>

    <para>For both the Windows and Unix-based development versions,
    VE-Launcher is a Python program. Run it in the same way as the Unix-based
    install. In development mode, VE-Launcher does not require dependencies to
    be set and it looks for stereo desktop configuration files in their build
    location, not their install location.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Preset Environmental Variables:</emphasis> Certain values,
    such as the <code>VPR_DEBUG_LEVEL</code>, can be automatically entered
    into VE-Launcher from the environment when VE-Launcher starts. If they are
    set in the environment, they overwrite the values saved from previous
    VE-Launcher sessions. These variables include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>VE_DEPS_DIR</code> (dependencies directory, Windows
        only)</para>

        <para>This is the base directory in which the VE-Suite dependencies
        installer places the associated files during a Windows install</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>VJ_BASE_DIR</code> (VR Juggler directory, Unix
        only)</para>

        <para>This is the base directory in which VR Juggler is installed
        during a Unix install</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>VE_WORKING_DIR</code> (working directory)</para>

        <para>This is the location of a desired application</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>TAO_MACHINE</code> (TAO machine)</para>

        <para>This is the computer on which VE-CE is being run. In Desktop
        Mode, this is set to the local machine and cannot connect to another
        computer. In other modes (i.e., Cluster Mode), the TAO_MACHINE is run
        on a single computer and the other nodes communicate with this
        computer.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>TAO_PORT</code> (TAO port)</para>

        <para>This is the port number on the TAO machine through which the
        communication is being passed</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>OSGNOTIFYLEVEL</code> (OSG debug level)</para>

        <para>This is a numeric value that assigns how much debug output is
        displayed for OpenSceneGraph (the scene graph that VE-Xplorer
        uses)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>VPR_DEBUG_ENABLE</code> (VPR debug)</para>

        <para>This is a yes/no value that assigns how much debug output is
        displayed for VR Juggler</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL (VPR debug level)</para>

        <para>This is a yes/no value that assigns how much debug output is
        displayed for VR Juggler</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting VE-Launcher's Dependencies</title>

    <para>Before VE-Suite can be run, VE-Launcher must be pointed to its
    dependencies. The process for doing this depends on whether VE-Suite is
    being run on a Windows- or Unix-based system.</para>

    <para>Pointing to the dependencies is bypassed completely in development
    mode because VE-Launcher assumes the enviromental variables have been
    set.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows:</emphasis> VE-Launcher needs to find
    the VE-Suite dependencies directory that was installed along with
    VE-Suite. The first time VE-Launcher is started, the user is prompted to
    choose the dependencies directory for it. This directory should be named
    <code>VE_Suite.#.#_Dependencies</code>.</para>

    <para>If necessary, you can change the dependencies directory by selecting
    Choose Dependencies from the Options menu in VE-Launcher.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Changing the dependencies directory in Windows</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-choose-deps.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">UNIX:</emphasis> VE-Launcher supports
    dependencies spread across multiple directories. The first time
    VE-Launcher is run, you will be asked to choose the directory for its
    dependencies. Each dependency's directory should be added to the
    list.</para>

    <para>The only exception is VR Juggler's dependency directory. Since it
    sets multiple variables, it needs to be chosen separately from the other
    dependencies.</para>

    <para>If necessary, you can change the the dependencies directory by
    selecting Choose Dependencies from the Options menu in VE-Launcher.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Changing the dependencies directory in UNIX</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-linux-choose-deps.jpg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Once the dependencies have been selected, VE-Launcher's main window
    displays.</para>

    <para>Development mode: VE-Launcher does not require dependencies in
    development mode. It assumes that the necessary environmental variables
    have already been set.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Basics</title>

    <para>VE-Launcher's main window displays the basic choices that need to be
    made before running VE-Suite. Here is a breakdown of what can be done from
    the main window:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>VE-Launcher's main window</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-window.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Working Directory: You can either type in the directory that
        contains the files you want to load, or you can browse the file system
        with the Choose Working Directoy button</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>CE (computational engine) Name and CE Port: Enter the computer
        and port you want to connect to</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Launch Mode: Select the desired mode. There are six
        options:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Desktop Mode launches VE-Conductor, Name Server, and
            VE-Xplorer in a synchronized manner for the convenience of using
            VE-Suite on a personal computer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tablet Mode launches VE-Conductor and is designed for use on
            tablets</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Computation Mode launches the Name Server and is designed
            for use on computational engines</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Visualization Mode launches VE-Xplorer and is designed for
            viewing projects</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Shell Mode lets the user work in a new shell with the
            VE-Suite environment set up. If Shell Mode is selected, you will
            be asked whether you want the shell to run VE-Builder. If you
            click Yes, the selected VE-Builder directory will be added to the
            path. On Windows, launching in Shell Mode creates the shell in a
            window. Simply close the window to exit the shell.</para>

            <para>On Unix, launching in Shell Mode makes the shell a child of
            your current terminal. Type <code>exit</code> to return to your
            original shell.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Custom Mode lets the user choose the settings.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The settings for every mode can be viewed and changed by clicking
    the Mode Settings button. Once you have chosen the appropriate settings,
    click Launch VE Suite to close VE-Launcher and start VE-Suite.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Launcher Menus</title>

    <para>VE-Launcher's main window has a menu bar with the following
    menus:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>File menu</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open....: Pick a <code>ves</code> or script shell file to
            launch</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Open Recent File: Pick a recently launched <code>ves</code>
            file or script shell file to launch</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Preferences: If necessary, select a default working
            directory rather than using the directory that was in use during
            the previous session</para>

            <figure>
              <title>VE-Launcher Preferences dialog box</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-preferences.png"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Close File: Remove any <code>ves</code> file or script
            shell</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Quit: Quit VE-Launcher</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Configurations menu</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Load: Load a previously saved VE-Launcher configuration.
            VE-Launcher configurations store information such as mode
            settings, VE-Xplorer configurations, and cluster settings</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Load Configuration dialog box</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-config.jpg"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Save: Save the current VE-Launcher configuration</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Delete: Delete a previously saved VE-Launcher
            configuration</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Options menu</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose Dependencies: Change the location of dependencies
            based on where the user has installed them</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Choose Builder Folder: Change the Builder directory (Windows
            only)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Set Debug Levels: Display the varying amounts of debug
            output for VR Juggler and OpenSceneGraph</para>

            <figure>
              <title>Debug Settings dialog box</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-options-debug.png"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Auto-Launch Passed Files: If checked, files passed as
            arguments to VE-Launcher are instantly launched. If unchecked,
            files passed as arguments are opened in VE-Launcher for the user
            to launch manually</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Cluster Wait Times: Customizes the time VE-Suite waits
            between starting the master node and its slave, and the time
            VE-Suite waits between starting individual slaves</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Help menu</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Mode Settings</title>

    <figure>
      <title>Click Mode Settings in VE-Launcher</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-mode-settings-button.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Click the Mode Settings button to view and change settings. The
    Desktop, Tablet, and Computation Modes display their settings in read-only
    mode. Visualization Mode allows Xplorer Configuration Mode and Cluster
    Settings (when Cluster Mode is selected) to be changed. Custom Mode allows
    every setting to be changed. Choices are displayed in read-only mode if
    they cannot be changed, or if changing them would not have any effect. For
    example, Xplorer Configuration Mode cannot be selected if VE-Xplorer is
    not being run.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Custom Mode Settings dialog box</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-custom-mode-settings.png"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Options that can be set include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>which VR Juggler configuration to use from the dropdown menu.
        Users can edit the list by clicking Edit Configuration List in the
        Xplorer Configuration Mode area of the Custom Mode Settings window.
        The configuration list will be discussed in more detail in the next
        section.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>which programs to run. Users can choose to run any combination
        of Name Server, Conductor, and Xplorer. At least one must be selected
        or VE-Suite will not launch.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>whether to run Conductor and Xplorer in Desktop Mode. This
        checkbox is disabled if neither is being launched.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>which mode to run Xplorer in. Users can choose between
        Non-Cluster Mode (single computer) or Cluster Mode. This radio list is
        disabled if Xplorer is not being launched.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Edit Configuration List</title>

      <figure>
        <title>Click the Edit Configuration List button</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-edit-conf-list.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>VE-Suite has multiple configuration files available. To help users
      keep track of them, VE-Launcher keeps a list of the configuration files
      used. Entries in this list can be added, renamed, or deleted. The path
      to the currently selected entry is listed in the field at the bottom of
      the window so you can tell which name stands for which file.</para>

      <para>When a new configuration is added to the list, its initial name is
      the same as its file name. The configuration should be renamed to be
      more descriptive.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Xplorer Configurations dialog box</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-xplorer-conf.png"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Unix Clusters</title>

    <para>VE-Launcher can run VE-Suite from one computer across a cluster. To
    use VE-Launcher's cluster functions on Unix, the cluster must satisfy
    these requirements:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The path to VE-Suite, its dependencies, and the working
        directory must be the same on every cluster node</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VE-Launcher's user must have permission to <link
        xlink:href="http://www.employees.org/~satch/ssh/faq/ssh-faq.html">ssh</link>
        to each mode</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The user must manually ssh into each node and authenticate its
        host</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>Once all the nodes have been authenticated, the cluster can be run
    from VE-Launcher:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If NameServer and Conductor are running on a certain node, open
        VE-Launcher from that node. (VE-Launcher runs NameServer and Conductor
        from the same computer VE-Launcher is running on.)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Set the settings and select the Cluster Xplorer Mode. The
        Cluster Settings button will then be enabled.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Custom Settings dialog box in UNIX</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-linux-cluster-settings.jpg"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click Cluster Settings. A window will open displaying master and
        slave lists. Type in the master’s name, add each slave’s name to the
        list, then click Ok.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Cluster Settings dialog box in UNIX</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/02-launcher-linux-cluster-settings-b.jpg"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click the Launch button to launch VE-Suite. VE-Suite will start
        on the cluster computers.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE:</emphasis> There is a slight delay
    between each node launched because simultaneous launching causes erratic
    behavior in clusters. The delay can be changed by selecting Cluster Wait
    Times from the Options menu. If sync or unconnected nodes cause problems
    using VE-Launcher, try lengthening the delays. If launching the cluster
    takes too long, try shortening them.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Windows Clusters</title>

    <para>VE-Launcher can start VE-Suite across a Windows cluster through
    <link vendor=""
    xlink:href="http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/bb897553.aspx">PsExec</link>.</para>

    <para>To use the cluster functions of VE-Launcher on Windows, the cluster
    must satisfy these requirements:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The path to VE-Suite, its dependencies, and the working
        directory are the same on every cluster node</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link userlevel=""
        xlink:href="http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/sysinternals/bb897553.aspx">PsExec</link>
        is installed on the computer that is running VE-Launcher</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>To launch the cluster:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>If NameServer and Conductor are running on a particular
        computer, open VE-Launcher from that computer (VE-Launcher runs
        NameServer and Conductor from the current computer)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select the appropriate settings. Set Xplorer Configuration to
        Cluster Mode. This causes the Cluster Settings button to be
        enabled.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Custom Mode Settings dialog box in Windows</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/02-cluster-settings-button.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click Cluster Settings. A window will open displaying the master
        and slave lists, plus an optional User name field. Type in the
        master’s name, then add each slave's name to the list.</para>

        <para>Some clusters might require the user to connect with a certain
        user name. If so, enter that user name into the User name field. The
        user name's domain may need to be included as well, depending on the
        cluster's setup. If you provide your user name, you will have to
        manually enter your password in each Psexec window as it launches.
        VE-Suite does not send passwords for security reasons.</para>

        <para>Extra variables can also be passed to cluster computers. Click
        on the Pass Extra Vars button and list any extra variables that you
        would like to pass, then click OK.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Cluster Settings dialog box in Windows</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/02-cluster-settings-window.png"></imagedata>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Launch VE-Suite by clicking Launch. The cluster computers will
        start up VE-Suite.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE: </emphasis>There is a slight delay
    between each node launched because simultaneous launching causes erratic
    behavior in clusters. The delay can be changed by selecting Cluster Wait
    Times from the Options menu. If sync or unconnected nodes cause problems
    using VE-Launcher, try lengthening the delays. If launching the cluster
    takes too long, try shortening them.</para>

    <para>The cluster template: If your cluster needs extra code to launch
    (for example, a net use command to set up a remote drive), the code can be
    entered into the <code>clusterTemplate.txt</code> file. Any terminal code
    in the <code>clusterTemplate.txt</code> file will run on the cluster’s
    other computer before VE-Xplorer is launched. Please read the comments in
    <code>clusterTemplate.txt</code> for more details.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>VE-Launcher Command Line Arguments</title>

    <para>Once VE-Launcher is set up, VE-Suite can be quickly started by
    passing arguments from the command line. Some arguments pass values to
    VE-Launcher while others bypass VE-Launcher completely and auto-launch
    VE-Suite. Arguments that auto-launch VE-Suite use the previously saved
    settings for any fields they do not change.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>&lt;file&gt;</code>: Passes a <code>.ves</code> file or
        shell script named &lt;<code>file?&gt;</code> to VE-Launcher.
        Auto-launches VE-Suite if Auto-Launch Passed Files has been selected
        in VE-Suite. Otherwise, VE-Launcher starts with the file
        loaded.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-q</code>, <code>--quick</code>: Auto-launches VE-Suite
        with its most recent settings</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-g&lt;config&gt;</code>,
        <code>--config=&lt;config&gt;</code>: Loads the VE-Launcher
        configuration named <code>&lt;config&gt;</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-d</code>, <code>--dev</code>: Starts VE-Launcher in
        Development mode</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-w&lt;dir&gt;</code>, <code>--dir=&lt;dir&gt;</code>:
        Auto-launches VE-Suite with the working directory set to
        <code>&lt;dir&gt;</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-t&lt;name&gt;</code>,
        <code>--taomachine=&lt;name&gt;</code>: Auto-launches VE-Suite with
        TAOMACHINE set to <code>&lt;name&gt;</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-p&lt;port&gt;</code>, <code>--port=&lt;port&gt;</code>:
        Auto-launches VE-Suite with port set to
        <code>&lt;port&gt;</code></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-j&lt;file&gt;</code>, <code>--jconf=&lt;file&gt;</code>:
        Auto-launches VE-Suite using <code>&lt;file&gt;</code> as VE-Xplorer's
        Juggler configuration</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-l&lt;boolean&gt;</code>,
        <code>--cluster=&lt;boolean&gt;</code>: If
        <code>&lt;boolean&gt;==True</code>, auto-launches VE-Suite in Cluster
        Mode. If <code>&lt;boolean&gt;==False</code>, auto-launches VE-Suite
        in Non-Cluster Mode.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-b</code>, <code>--debug</code>: Auto-launches VE-Suite
        and debugs the launch</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Program arguments set certain parts of VE-Suite to run. They
        auto-launch VE-Suite, running the programs specified. Note that only
        the programs specified in the arguments are run. For example, if a
        user only passes <code>-x -n</code>, only VE-Xplorer and the
        computational engine will run, even if the default settings usually
        run VE-Conductor as well.</para>

        <para>The program arguments are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><code>-n</code>, <code>--nameserver</code>: Runs the
            computational engine</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>-c</code>, <code>--conductor</code>: Runs
            VE-Conductor</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>-x</code>, <code>-xplorer</code>: Runs
            VE-Xplorer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><code>-s</code>, <code>-shell</code>: Runs a shell with
            VE-Suite's environment set</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Example</title>

    <para>John Doe wants to set up VE-Suite to look at a virtual power plant
    design. He needs to start it in Visualization Mode, using the VR Juggler
    configuration "standalone". He also needs VE-Suite to connect to computer
    <code>kiwi</code> on port 1239.</para>

    <para>When John starts VE-Launcher, he sees this:</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-jd-launcher-window.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>First, John types the path to the plant design data directory in the
    Working Directory field. He could also use the Choose Working Directory
    button to find it.</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-jd-launcher-window-b.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>John needs to change the computational engine (CE) name, but he
    cannot because VE-Launcher is currently in Desktop Mode, which
    automatically sets the CE name to <code>localhost</code>. To unlock the CE
    name, he switches to Visualization Mode. Remember that any mode besides
    Desktop Mode will allow users to change the CE name.</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-jd-launcher-window-c.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Switching modes unlocks the CE name and sets it to the last
    user-input value. Now John can change the CE name and port.</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-jd-launcher-window-d.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To finish setting up VE-Launcher, John must change the mode's
    settings. He clicks the Mode Settings button to bring up the Settings
    window.</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-jd-launcher-mode-settings.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Visualization Mode sets most of the options, and the Non-Cluster
    Xplorer Configuration Mode is already selected. That leaves changing the
    Xplorer Configuration. However, the configuration that John needs is not
    on the list. He clicks the Edit Configuration List button.</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-jd-launcher-xplorer-config.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>John clicks the Add button, which opens the <code>configFiles</code>
    directory. He selects the appropriate file and clicks Open.</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-jd-launcher-choose-config.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The configuration is added to the list with the same filename that
    it had in the <code>configFiles</code> directory. In this case, that name
    is <code>standalone.jconf</code>. John clicks the Rename button to rename
    it "Plant Design" so he can remember which project it is for.</para>

    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/02-jd-launcher-rename-standalone.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Now that he has finished editing the list, John exits the Xplorer
    Configurations window. Because Plant Design was selected when he exited,
    it is automatically set as his current configuration file. With everything
    set up appropriately, John can now click the Launch VE-Suite button to
    look at the design.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
