<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>VE-Suite Documentation</title>

    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname />

        <surname />
      </personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname />
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
  </info>

  <preface>
    <title>Introduction to VE-Suite</title>

    <para>VE-Suite is an open source virtual engineering software toolkit. The
    toolkit enables the user to simultaneously interact with engineering
    analyses and graphical models to create a virtual decision-making
    environment.</para>

    <para>In nearly all aspects of the engineering process-design,
    manufacturing, and maintenance-the tools employed at each phase rely on
    virtual models (e.g., software tools) to reduce cost and shorten
    development time. This results in a wider variety of software tools being
    used across a wide range of vendors and engineering firms. In this
    environment, engineers are required to manually move information from one
    software package to another. Thus, the process does not support real-time,
    collaborative design in which the engineer establishes the dynamic
    thinking process needed to obtain an intuitive feel for the performance of
    a product. It also does not permit the real-time exploration of questions
    raised by other engineers, designers, or managers. This working
    arrangement significantly lessens the number of alternatives that can be
    investigated, limits the essential creative design process, and
    discourages "what if" questions that allow breakthroughs in design. The
    result of this situation is that the engineer ends up shifting his or her
    focus from engineering to manual integration of information. To allow
    engineers to focus on engineering, a new workflow and paradigm is needed.
    This new workflow is described within a new enabling technology called
    virtual engineering and is implemented via VE-Suite. Using VE-Suite to
    implement virtual engineering reduces the design cycle time to allow new
    technologies to reach production and operation more quickly than
    previously possible.</para>

    <para>Engineering tools and information need to be integrated throughout
    each engineering project. That is, information from the design phase needs
    to be available to design and manufacturing contractors without manual
    reentry or other hassles. Currently, for a variety of reasons (e.g.,
    budgetary constraints, inter-company politics), no commercial software
    package has the capability to integrate information from the complete
    product design team from economists and numerical modelers to design and
    manufacturing firms. VE-Suite addresses this constraint by creating a tool
    with open interfaces that allows other commercial and open-source packages
    to exchange data in a comprehensive design environment. In this
    environment, all the data and tools necessary to make a particular
    engineering decision are available to the stakeholder trying to move the
    engineering process forward.</para>

    <para>VE-Suite is intended to be used in the engineering process, whether
    for business model investigation or training. VE-Suite is used in a
    diverse set of engineering applications to allow engineers and other
    project stakeholders to gain insight into complex engineering
    problems.</para>
  </preface>

  <part>
    <title>User's Guide</title>

    <partintro>
      <para>To start using VE-Suite, skip to Chapter 3, Creating Content in
      VE-Suite.</para>
    </partintro>

    <!-- TODO: add olink for Chapter 3 -->

    <xi:include href="Chapter01.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter02.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter03.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter04.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter05.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter06.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter07.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter08.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter09.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>Developer Information</title>

    <xi:include href="Chapter10.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter11.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter12.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter13.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter14.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter15.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter16.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter17.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter18.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter19.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter20.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter21.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter22.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />

    <xi:include href="Chapter23.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>Other Tools</title>

    <xi:include href="Chapter24.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />
  </part>

  <xi:include href="AppendixA.xml"
              xpointer="element(/1)" />
</book>
