<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>VE-Suite Documentation</title>

  <preface>
    <title>Introduction to VE-Suite</title>

    <para>VE-Suite is an open source virtual engineering software toolkit. The
    toolkit enables the user to simultaneously interact with engineering
    analyses and graphical models to create a virtual decision-making
    environment.</para>

    <para>In nearly all aspects of the engineering process-design,
    manufacturing, and maintenance-the tools employed at each phase rely on
    virtual models (e.g., software tools) to reduce cost and shorten development
    time. This results in a wider variety of software tools being used across
    a wide range of vendors and engineering firms. In this environment,
    engineers are required to manually move information from one software
    package to another. Thus, the process does not support real-time,
    collaborative design in which the engineer establishes the dynamic thinking
    process needed to obtain an intuitive feel for the performance of a
    product. It also does not permit the real-time exploration of questions
    raised by other engineers, designers, or managers. This working arrangement
    significantly lessens the number of alternatives that can be investigated,
    limits the essential creative design process, and discourages "what if"
    questions that allow breakthroughs in design. The result of this situation
    is that the engineer ends up shifting his or her focus from engineering to
    manual integration of information. To allow engineers to focus on
    engineering, a new workflow and paradigm is needed. This new workflow is
    described within a new enabling technology called virtual engineering and
    is implemented via VE-Suite. Using VE-Suite to implement virtual engineering
    reduces the design cycle time to allow new technologies to reach production
    and operation more quickly than previously possible.</para>

    <para>Engineering tools and information need to be integrated throughout
    each engineering project. That is, information from the design phase needs
    to be available to design and manufacturing contractors without manual
    reentry or other hassles. Currently, for a variety of reasons (e.g.,
    budgetary constraints, inter-company politics), no commercial software
    package has the capability to integrate information from the complete
    product design team from economists and numerical modelers to design and
    manufacturing firms. VE-Suite addresses this constraint by creating a tool
    with open interfaces that allows other commercial and open-source packages
    to exchange data in a comprehensive design environment. In this environment,
    all the data and tools necessary to make a particular engineering decision
    are available to the stakeholder trying to move the engineering process
    forward.</para>

    <para>VE-Suite is intended to be used in the engineering process, whether
    for business model investigation or training. VE-Suite is used in a diverse
    set of engineering applications to allow engineers and other project
    stakeholders to gain insight into complex engineering problems.</para>
  </preface>

  <part>
    <title>User's Guide</title>

    <xi:include href="chapter_1_installation_and_setup.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_2_launcher.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_3_running_vesuite.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_4_visualizations.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_5_vebuilder.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />
  </part>

  <part>
    <title>Developer Information</title>

    <xi:include href="chapter_6_code_guidelines.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_7_building_vesuite.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_8_dependencies.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_9_setting_the_environment.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_10_description_of_the_engines.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_11_software_development_documents.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="chapter_12_software_development_tools.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" />
  </part>
</book>
