<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
  <title>Installation and Setup</title>

  <para>Support is provided at the following locations:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><ulink url="http://www.vesuite.org/forum/">VE-Suite Forums</ulink>
      - Users/developers can go here to access forums.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><ulink
      url="https://subversion.vrac.iastate.edu/Subversion/TSVEG/Bugzilla/">VE-Suite
      Bugzilla</ulink> - VE-Suite's interface for bug tracking. Users and
      developers can view and submit bugs.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Installation of VE-Suite is fairly straightforward. Visit the <ulink
  url="http://www.vesuite.org/download.php">Downloads</ulink> section and
  locate your operating system.</para>
  
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Windows:</emphasis> Two installers, which guide
  you through the process of selecting various options, are provided for
  Windows. One installer, vesuite#.#.#_####.exe, contains the core VE-Suite
  binaries and .dll files. The dependencies installer, vesuite_deps#.#.#.exe,
  contains the binaries and .dll files of VE-Suite's dependencies, arranged into
  include, bin, lib, and share subdirectories.</para>  

  <para><emphasis role="bold">UNIX:</emphasis> A tar.gz file of the current
  release of VE-Suite is provided. You can extract the VE-Suite.#.#.# directory
  from it. Instead of one central Dependencies folder, we provide the
  dependencies' RPM files. Be sure to install each dependency you need before
  you run VE-Suite.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Windows Installation</title>

    <para>Installing VE-Suite and its dependencies follows the same procedure
    as other installations. You'll choose which components to install, their
    locations, their Start Menu folder, and whether to have a desktop
    icon.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="veimages/windowsinstall.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Of particular note is which components to install. In large setups,
    certain computers will run the NameServer while others will handle the
    Conductor and Xplorer. If you only plan to run it on a single desktop,
    you'll want to install everything. Just leave all the checkboxes
    checked.</para>

    <para>Go through the same process for VE-Suite's dependencies.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="unix_installation">
    <title>UNIX Installation</title>

    <para>On Unix, the installers are compressed tar.gz files. You can open
    them using these commands:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Using GNU tar:</para>

        <para><code>gtar xvzf vesuite_#.#.#_RHEL_4.tar.gz </code></para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Using gzip:</para>

        <para><code>gunzip &lt; vesuite_#.#.#_RHEL_4.tar.gz | tar xvf
        -</code></para>

      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">NOTE:</emphasis> These examples use
    vesuite_#.#.# as a general placeholder for any version of VE-Suite. Be
    sure to change the version number to the specific version you are
    installing.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="setting_runtime_environment">
    <title>Setting the Runtime Environment</title>

    <para>In previous versions, VE-Suite's runtime environment was set through
    text scripts. Now it uses VE-Launcher to set up the environment. Most of
    it is automated, but you need to be aware of two important variables it
    sets: VE-Suite's directory and VE-Suite's Dependencies directory.</para>

    <para>VE-Launcher automatically determines VE-Suite's directory from the
    current working directory. Moving the Launcher out of VE-Suite's directory
    or starting it from a different directory will pass the wrong value to
    VE-Suite, causing errors.</para>

    <para>The Dependencies directory is the only variable you need to set
    manually. The first time you start VE-Launcher, you will be asked to find
    the Dependencies directory. On Windows, it is the
    VE_Suite.#.#.#_Dependencies folder.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="veimages/runtimeenv1.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>On Unix/Linux, multiple dependencies can be chosen. The only one
    you need to specifically select is VR-Juggler's directory.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="veimages/launcherbasics2.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>If you're upgrading from an earlier version of VE-Suite, you can
    also reset the Dependencies directory by clicking the Change Dependencies
    Folder button in VE-Launcher.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="setting_linux_menus">
    <title>Setting Menus, Icons, Filetypes on Linux</title>
    
    <para>VE-Suite comes with a vesuiteConfig.sh script you can use to set
    up menus, icons, and filetypes for VE-Suite on Linux desktop systems. The
    script works for Gnome 2.8+ and KDE.</para>
    <para>To run it, enter its directory and type in
    '<code>./vesuiteConfig.sh</code>', followed by the arguments. The script
    accepts these arguments:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">--gnome or --kde:</emphasis> Sets Gnome or
        KDE as the primary desktop. If neither argument is passed, Gnome is
        chosen as the default primary desktop.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">--both:</emphasis> Installs on both Gnome
        and KDE. --gnome or --kde still need to be passed to set the primary
        desktop, because on most dual-desktop systems, one desktop inherits some
        preferences from the other.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">--user or --global:</emphasis> Sets the
        installations to either user-only or all-users. If neither argument is
        passed, all-users is chosen if you have root access; other user-only
        is chosen.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">--uninstall:</emphasis> Uninstalls the setup
        passed. Goes with any other passed arguments. Example: '--gnome --global
        --uninstall' would uninstall the setup created by passing '--gnome
        --global'.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

  </section>
</chapter>
